<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The burning yet un-consumed bush, or, The holinesse of places discuss'd held forth in two farewel-sermons at Christ-Church London, August 17th, 1662 / by William Jenkins.</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28952</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10785046</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10785046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46802)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1387:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The burning yet un-consumed bush, or, The holinesse of places discuss'd held forth in two farewel-sermons at Christ-Church London, August 17th, 1662 / by William Jenkins.</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Farewell sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45865:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45865:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BURNING, Yet Un-conſumed BUSH: OR The Holineſs of Places diſcuſs'd.</p>
            <p>Held forth in Two Farevvel-Sermons at <hi>Chriſt-Church London, Auguſt</hi> 17th. 1662.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>WILLIAM JENKINS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 23.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Now theſe are the laſt words of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45865:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45865:2"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words of a dying man uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are very ſerious, weighty, and much regarded: The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Notes being this Preachers laſt Legacy to his Congregation, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his civil, though voluntary death, by reaſon of the great concourſe of People that were then aſſembled to leave their dying Paſtor preach his own Funeral Sermon whilſt he was yet
<pb facs="tcp:45865:3"/>alive, many being too diſtant from him, or too much diſturbed by the croud, fell ſhort of their ſhare and portion in them: For the benefit of ſuch as well as other, who loſt much by committing to memory, are theſe Notes expoſed to publike view; I conceive I need not add any one Letter to take off the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor that hath bin caſt upon him, as if out of Humour and Faction, or which is worſe, diſobedience to Authority, he refuſed to conform; enough you will find here to give an account why he choſe to take up his Croſs, and follow Chriſt in a way of Conſcience and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45865:3"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>JENKINS</hi>'s Forenoon SERMON <hi>Aug.</hi> 17. 1662.</head>
            <head type="sub">TEXT:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HEBR. 11.38.</bibl> The former Part of the Verſe, <hi>Of whom the World was not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Apoſtle in this excellent Chapter (that by ſome is deſervedly called, a little Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs) diſcovers the triumph of Faith, or victory againſt all difficulty we meet with:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Faith it aſſents to Truths be they never ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It puts men upon Duties, be they never ſo irrational, or againſt carnal Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It inables to ſufferings, be they never ſo affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive. Theſe Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thies went through all by the victory that overcame the world, the bitterneſs as well as the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45865:4"/>
            <p>In theſe Verſes the Apoſtle doth two things: Firſt, He ſets down the greatneſs and ſmartneſs of their ſufferings, which are by ſome Learned men reduced to three Heads:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe ſufferings that were to tempt them, and draw them from God, by thoſe pains and tortures they were to undergo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe ſufferings they underwent in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Their ſufferings in regard of wandring and leaving their comforts, rather then they would looſe God.</p>
            <p>There were all kind of perſecutions laid upon theſe Saints, through all which they waded, and never would be brought to forſake God and his truth, for any of them. 2. We have here the excellency of the ſufferer, and that is in that expreſſion, <hi>Theſe men,</hi> or <hi>theſe perſons,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n they were under all theſe diſtreſſes from the world, yet they were ſuch of whom the world was not worthy.</p>
            <p>Brethren, The excellency of theſe Saints and ſervants of God is conſiderable two ways, that we may proceed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and clearly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reference to the wicked, their excellency was ſo great that the wicked world was not worthy of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their excellency is diſcovered from the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate or judgment that the Apoſtle paſſes upon them, who tells us, that he accounted them to be ſuch, though they were under ſuch diſtreſſes and troubles, yet they were a people of whom the world was not worthy.</p>
            <p>I ſhall fall upon the due eſtimation the bleſſed Apoſtle raiſes upon theſe perſecuted Saints, who was enlightned by the Spirit of God, and ſo was able to paſſe a right ſentence upon theſe perſecuted Saints; from this I raiſe this enſuing Obſervation.</p>
            <p>Obſerv. <hi>That a godly man doth ſee a very great worth and excellency in the people of God in the midſt of all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45865:4"/>and diſtreſſes;</hi> Or, <hi>That a godly man, a gracious heart, one that hath ſpiritual Spectacles, does ſee an excellency and worth in the people of God, in the midſt of all trouble and perſecution that can befall them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I ſhall handle it firſt doctrinally according to my conſtant method, then come to improve it by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. For the Doctrinal handling of it, there are two things muſt be diſcovered;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Wherein the high eſtimation of a gracious heart does appear, wherein it doth diſcover it ſelf, wherein they ſhew they have ſuch an high eſtimation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whence it is, and how it comes to paſs, that godly men have this high and honourable eſteem of the Saints and people of God in their troubles and diſtreſſes which befall them.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, Wherein the high eſtimation of a gracious heart does appear, I ſhall ſhew it in five or ſix following particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It appears in this, In that they are not aſhamed of owning their perſons and faith, that they profeſs in their troubles and diſtreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; the ſociety of the people of God, and the fellowſhip of the Faith and profeſſion, is highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by a gracious heart, let the Saints lye under never ſo great diſtreſſes. This is manifeſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 25. and 26. Verſes of this Chapter, <hi>He choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to injoy all the pleaſure and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>Court.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Religion the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true God, and owning the faith and thoſe Truths the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſtood up for, this was that which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> would not deſert: and thence it was he did not deſert their company and ſociety, but went and viſited them when they lay under thoſe burthens under which they lay.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond thing wherein is diſcovered ſo high an eſtimation of the Saints and people of God in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, is their ſympathizing, and follow-feeling with them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45865:5"/>in their ſufferings, if it goes ill with the Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, all the reſt ſympathizes with them; if one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffers all the reſt ſuffer. Inſtance, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> (who had the greateſt favour of the greateſt Prince then on earth) he lookt with a ſad countenance becauſe of the ſufferings of the Saints and people of God; <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Wherefore the King ſaid unto me, Why is thy countenance ſad, ſeeing thou art not ſick? this is nothing elſe but ſorrow of heart. Then I was very ſore afraid, and anſwered the King, Becauſe of the diſtreſſes the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God lie under:</hi> The pleaſure of Muſick ſhould never be with him, ſays <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal</hi> 137.6. <hi>If I do not remember th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth; if I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief joy.</hi> As it is with two ſtrings in an inſtrument rightly tuned, if one be touched, the other trembles; if one ſervant of Chriſt be in a ſuffering condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the reſt ſuffers with him; this is the damp of all worldly delight, if it be ill with any of the people of God the reſt ſuffer in the way of compaſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In that they can plead for them, and take their parts, when they are never ſo much out of favour, when they are never ſo much deſpiſed and abuſed: This was in the caſe of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> how he pleaded for poor <hi>David</hi> before his cruel father <hi>Saul,</hi> though <hi>Saul</hi> called him a curſed ſon, and fell foul on his mother becauſe of him. See this in the caſe of <hi>Eſther,</hi> though it was death to go in to the King to plead for the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet for all this ſhe ſays, <hi>If I periſh, I periſh;</hi> reſolved I am, come what will come of it, in I will go, I can die, but I cannot be ſilent.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In that they will relieve them, and help and ſupply them with all needful good things they can, if they cannot do what they would, they will do for them what they can: See this in the caſe of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chap. 38. verſ. 8, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Ebedmelech went forth out of the Kings houſe, and ſpake to the King—: So</hi> Ebedmelech <hi>took the men with him, and went into the houſe of the king under the treaſury, and took thence old caſt clouts, and old rotten rags, and let them down by cords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45865:5"/>the dungeon to</hi> Jeremiah. <hi>And</hi> Ebedmel on <hi>the Ethiopian ſaid unto</hi> Jeremiah, <hi>Put now theſe old caſt clouts, and rotten rags under thine arm-holes under the cords. And</hi> Jeremiah <hi>did ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> So they drew up</hi> Jeremiah <hi>with cords, and took him up out of the dungeon, and</hi> Jeremiah <hi>remained in the court of the priſon.</hi> He would never be quiet, till he had got the Prophet out of the dungeon, and though the cords were lined with rags, yet more with love, and this ſavour of <hi>Ebedmelech</hi> God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4. <hi>Obadiahs</hi> maſter was not only an oppreſſor of the Saints and Prophets of God, but a very great perſecutor: This good man <hi>Obadiah</hi> took and hid 400 <hi>Prophets of the Lord and fed them with bread and water:</hi> (I will not undertake to propheſie to you this day, yet time may come when bread and water may be good food for a faithful Prophet.) Here note the gracious diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good <hi>Obadiah;</hi> as well as the providence of God in this act. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18. <hi>The Lord give mercy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of</hi> Oneſiphorus, <hi>for he oft refreſhed me, and was not aſhamed of my chain. But when he was in</hi> Rome, <hi>he ſought me out very diligently and found me. The Lord grant unto him, that he may finde mercy of the Lord in that day: and in how many thing's he miniſtred unto me at</hi> Epheſus, <hi>thou knoweſt very well.</hi> A moſt admirable Scripture to this purpoſe; Bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> being thrown into priſon, being in bonds, <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten refreſht him, and was not aſhamed of his chains? How did he ſhew this? When he was in <hi>Rome,</hi> he ſought him out diligently; By the way note, That <hi>Rome</hi> was the place where the cruel <hi>Nero</hi> was Emperour, it was the place where much blood of the Martyrs was ſpilt, yet there this good man ſought out <hi>Paul</hi> diligently: Mark what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, which is the prayer of <hi>Paul, The Lord grant to him that he may find mercy of the Lord in that day.</hi> I profeſs Sirs, I had rather have the prayers of <hi>Paul,</hi> then the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the greateſt Court on earth: Chriſtians, it is the greateſt treaſure in your houſe, to have the prayers of good men to God for you: You that have ſhewn your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45865:6"/>great and abundant love to the Saints and Servants of God in diſtreſs: I do from my ſoul beg the like mercy for you, that whatever you have done for his, may be ten thouſand times made up by him, that you may find mercy in that day, and truly Sirs, in that day mercy will be worth receiving.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They ſupplicate to God for them, they do not go to the Throne of Grace for themſelves, but <hi>Sion</hi> is in their thoughts. I am confident it is ſo with ſome, and am perſwaded it is ſo with all; they never beg daily bread for themſelves, but they remember <hi>Sion:</hi> In the 51 Pſalm, <hi>David</hi> was under trouble of Conſcience, ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouble, which is the ſoul of trouble, yet at the latter end of the 51 Pſalm he breaks out into this earneſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to God. <hi>Do good in thy good pleaſure unto Sion, build thou up the walls of</hi> Jeruſalem: So long as it is ill with the people of God, ſo long they are earneſt with God; and though they cannot overcome men with their prayers (which by the way they are to endeavour) yet they will never leave ſupplicating the Almighty, till they have overcome. As the ſufferings of Gods people are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of God, ſo they are in the ſight of the people of God.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſhew whence it is, That there is ſuch an high eſteem in the people of God, of the people of God, when under trouble and diſtreſs; for this take two Heads of Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard of thoſe of the people of God that do behold their ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In regard of thoſe people of God that are in ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard thoſe of the people of God, that do behold their ſufferings, troubles and diſtreſſes, in three regards.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe of the people of God that look upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in trouble, though they are ſuch as may differ from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45865:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, in regard of outward eſtate; one may be in honour, the other in diſhonour, yet they have an intereſt in the ſame head, and do belong to the ſame body that they do; they are not wooden leggs, nor glaſſe eyes; therefore Chriſt is called the ommon aviour, and the Saviour of the body, the whole Church: Faith it is called, the <hi>like precious faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 ch. in the beginning. The ſaith of one believer does as trnely lay hold on Chriſt, as the ſaith of another. This ſalvation is called common ſalvation: my meaning is, this outward diſproportion, as to birth and education, puts no difference at all in a ſpiritual reſpect, between believer and believer: a King and a Beggar all one in Chriſt; a <hi>Iew</hi> or a <hi>Greek,</hi> a great Scholar, or a poor ignorant man, as to the ſpiritual ſtate, all one, made happy the ſame way.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe they look at Spiritual excellency, and are able to diſcern ſpiritual excellency; they have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Judgement, as they look upon their old courſes and ſinnes with a new eye, ſo they look upon their company with a new e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: thoſe that before they highly eſteem'd they now diſeſteem: thoſe perſons that before hey eſteem'd a damp to their mirth, they now look upon them as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ones of the earth <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>The righteous is more excellent than his neighbour.</hi> In the 16 Pſalme, ſayes <hi>David My goodneſſe extends not to thee, but to the Saints; the excellent ones in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m is all my delight.</hi> Here was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed eſtimation, <hi>David</hi> ſaw excellency in theſe which worldlings deſpiſed. A carnal eye ſees no glory but in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal objects; Worlding bleſſe the Covetous, whom the Lord abhorrs. A gracious heart ſees a ſpiritual worth in a man diveſted of worldly enjoyments, as a curious eye may, and does ſee a great deal of Art and Curioſity in a picture, though in a broken frame. A Beaſt can ſee the ſhining of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, but knowes not the worth of it; a beaſt will rather lick up a lock of Hay, then a Diamond, though of never ſo great value. A wicked man wants a ſpirit of diſcerning. The people of God are the Workmanſhip of God, which a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45865:7"/>godly man is very much taken withall; not with the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, but with the goodneſſe that is in them. The four Monarchs of the earth is expreſt by four beaſts, which ſhews their cruelty, not their curioſity, in obſerving that of God which may be obſerved. A child is taken with the Gay, but a Learned man is taken with the Learning, and Art of a leſſon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A child of God, is one that highly eſteemes the people of God, judging of them as God judges. The child eſteems as the father eſteems: if the father cannot love any one, the ingenious child cannot endure that he ſhould come into the houſe. The Courtier followes the favorite of the King; whom the King honours, they cringe to. But to be ſure it is true as to ſpirituals: God judges not by the gold ring, or ſilken ſhute; a ſinner is a vile perſon in Gods account, and ſo he is in a godly mans account; God is more taken with a broken-hearted ſigh, than with all the gaudery in <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple. He did not chuſe the Eagle, or the Lion for ſacrifice, but the Lamb and the Dove: not many noble, not many rich, but the poor hath God cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: He that hath the life of God, he hath the love of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Is from the people of God that are beheld. This will appear in five or ſix particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The people of God, thoſe that are truely ſuch let their preſent condition be what it will, their end ſhall be happy. Men are not regarded in reference to what they have in poſſeſſion, but what they ſhall have in reverſion: the poor her care rich in faith, and ſhall be rich in glory. 1 <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 3 <hi>ch.</hi> The people of God are Heires of glory, coheires with Chriſt; when he ſhall appear, they ſhall appear with him in Glory: they are not poſſeſſors here but they are Heires, and are to be look'd upon as what they ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: Here they are Princes going to their Crown, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they ſhall be poſſeſſed of it: Here they may be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed baniſh'd, diſgrac'd, libeli'd, hereafter they ſhall ſhine as the Sun in Glory.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45865:7"/>
            <p n="2">2dly. They are not only ſuch as ſhall be happy, but they are very uſefull and beneficiall in the world, they are thoſe for whoſe ſake the world was made, they are the great common bleſſings of the world, like fire and water, they are thoſe for whoſe ſake God ſpares the world. If God would have ſpared the City for ten righteous perſons ſake, ſurely for many tens God ſpares the world; thoſe that are pull'd down by the world, are thoſe for whoſe ſake God doth not pull down the world, they are the ſoul of the world, as I may ſo ſay; If God had gathered in all his Elect, the world would not continue one hour longer.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. The excellency of their performances is highly eſteemed, there is a worth in every Holy work that Worldlings are not able to diſcern; Every Heavenly Prayer, and ſincerely beſtowed Almes, hath a worth that a carnall eye does not ſee: <hi>Luther</hi> ſayes, <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do the leaſt truly good work, then obtain all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of</hi> Caeſar <hi>and</hi> Alexander; if their good works ſhall be ſo rewarded, do you think a holy man can ſee them and not be taken with them? Many a wicked man when he hears a holy man make an excellent Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wiſhes that he could do ſo too, it is not from the goodneſſe he obſerves in it, or the principle from whence it comes, but from ſomething of naturall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments that he is taken with it; ſo a Godly man when he hears another Pray excellently, and live holily, he wiſhes from his heart that he could do ſo too, his aim is to grow in Holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. The preſent privileges of the people of God, not only what they ſhall have hereafter, but what they have here, they are freed from a world of Evils that Worldlings lye under, whatever befalls them turns to their benefit, they may be afflicted, but not hurt by affliction; the greateſt hurt the world does to them, tends to their greateſt good; Worldlings may take
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45865:8"/>away their Heads, they cannot their Crown: There is a reall communication of a bleſſed intereſt in all that is good, for they have an intereſt in all that God hath or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; the power of God is theirs to protect them, the love of God is ſet upon them, the righteouſneſſe of God imputed to them, ſo as to acquit them from ſin; ſo that a childe of God may not only appeal to the bowells of Gods mercy, but to the bar of Juſtice, all the providences of God ſhall tend to their good; in the 25. Pſalm, about the 10th. verſe, the Holy Ghoſt ſayes, <hi>All the wayes of God are Mercy and Truth, to them that are in Covenant with him;</hi> they are Mercy becauſe they are appointed to do them good, and Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhall certainly do them good; Chriſt, and God, and all is laid out for the good of a Godly man. In this world they may go to God and tell him wherein they are troubled, pained, or afflicted, and they are never more welcome to him, then when they ask moſt from him; if thou askes great things from God, God is well taken with ſuch requeſts, but if thou askes Riches and Honours, theſe are the low things of the Foot-ſtool: God is exceedingly taken with thee when thou askeſt Peace and Pardon, Peace of Conſcience, Pardon of Sin, Strength againſt Sin, Power to overcome thy Luſts, to withſtand Temptations; The people of God may have from God all that they want, and all they can regularly wiſh.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. Theſe are ſuch as have an incomparable dear and near relation to God, they are his delight, they are ſet apart by God as his own, his peculiar people; though God have a propriety in all, yet he hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar propriety in, and relation to theſe, therefore they are called his Children, his Houſe, his Jewells, his Garden; Gods whole Treaſure and Portion is his people; as God is his peoples portion, ſo his people are his portion, they are thoſe that he hath been at a great deal of coſt to purchaſe.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45865:8"/>
            <p n="6">6thly. They are ſuch as have the Image of God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon them, take notice of this word Image, for the Image of God appears in Holineſſe; Now an Image does not repreſent any thing of imperfection or deformity, but of Excellency. If a man takes the Picture of a man, he will not take it of his backſide, Leg, or Hand, or the like, but of his Face, his beautifulleſt part is chiefly aimed at in the Picture; Wicked men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Gods bounty in having wit and wealth, this is not the Image of God, the Image of God is that which is moſt excellent in a man, which is Holineſſe: The power of God is the Hand of God, the Wiſedome of God is the Eye of God, the Holineſſe of God is the Face, the Beauty of God, the people of God reſemble God in Purity, <hi>Be ye Holy as your Heavenly Father is Holy,</hi> there's the Pattern, they have the Divine Nature, 2 Pet. 1.4. <hi>Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promiſes, that by theſe you might be partakers of the divine nature, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.</hi> Epheſ. 4.18. <hi>Having the understanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of their heart.</hi> Rom. 3 23 <hi>For all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God.</hi> There is more of God in Grace, then in all the works that ever God did in the World beſides; there is much of God ſeen in making the Sun, Moon, and Stars, but in giving a man a new Nature, a renewed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in changing of a man from being a Veſſel of wrath, and Veſſel of Sathan, in making of him become a new man, a Veſſel of Glory; God ſhews more of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf then in making ten thouſand worlds</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Here I ſhall raiſe theſe following Inferences: If it be ſo that there is ſuch an excellency in the people of God here, then firſt, what excellency ſhall there be ſeen on the people of God in Heaven? If they are ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their rags, what will they be when they appear
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45865:9"/>in their Robes? The Glory of Chriſt ſhall be admired in them that believe. Oh what a Head is he that hath ſuch members? What a Lord is he that hath ſuch Attendance? The people of God are in a ſtate of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appearance now, hereafter it ſhall appear what they are, the very wicked themſelves ſhall admire them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Inference.</hi> What are we to think of thoſe that have no regard either for Religion, or for Religions ones, any farther forth then it is deckt and adorn'd with advantagious Beauty and outward Glory? If Religion be not lookt upon with a favourable Eye from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, farewell Religion and Religiouſneſſe. Theſe love the Child for the Nurſes ſake, what is the thing in faſhion theſe are for, what Authority commands they'le creep and cringe too; When the Dear is ſhot, the Heard flies from her, when Religion is ſhot at, then farewell Religion; what is this but to have the Faith of God in reſpect of Perſons? If I love Religion for the countenance of Authority, then it is certain I love Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion for the Authorities ſake; This is a ſign thou ſhalt not have communion with thoſe hereafter that thou contemneſt here: If the people of God are too bad for thee when they are in trouble and affliction, they will be too good for thee in Glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Inference.</hi> Note here the excellency of Holineſſe above Wordly Glory; Here a man is dignified by what is conferr'd upon him, when outward Honour ceaſeth, the man is contemned, but Holineſſe it dignifies a man, and ſhall remain here and hereafter; Set a Gyant in a valley he is a Gyant ſtill, a Pearl is a Pearl though on a dunghill, a Holy man is a Holy man though never ſo much diſgraſt and contemned by men: <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had a Leathern Girdle, and had Locuſt for his food, yet there was not a greater then <hi>John Baptist</hi> born of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; He was the forerunner of Chriſt, the Friend of the Bridegroom; on the other ſide <hi>Herod,</hi> that was like the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45865:9"/>Voyce of God, and not of man, what was he in Gods account? The Angel ſmote him and he became Worms meat. There is a ſilent dignity in reproached piety, and a ſilent ignominy in advanced iniquity: As it was with Chriſt, ſo it is with the Servants of Chriſt, when he was on Earth no man had more ignominy poured upon him, yet there was a ſecret Glory attended him in all that befell him, though Born in a Manger, yet Worſhipped there, ſometimes he was driven to be hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, the Fiſh brought him money, ſometimes a weary, at that very time converts a Woman, ſometimes laid hold on by his Enemies, at that very time his Enemies fell down before him; Look through the whole courſe of his life, there was a ſecret glory under all ignominy: Juſt thus it is with the Servants of Chriſt, they are in trouble and diſgrace, but there is a ſecret Glory and dignity ſhines in them, the Spirit of God and of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſts upon them, if ye ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake bleſſed are ye, to be in high place and yet to be a Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, or a Swearer, or a Whoremaſter, or Prophane, this ſpoyles all thy glory, be thou never ſo high.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Inference.</hi> This is the way for a man to have a good name; wouldſt thou gain a good report living and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Take heed of ſin, take heed of diſhonoring God, then God will have thee in everlaſting remembrance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Inference.</hi> Note here the certain happineſſe of theſe beholders, that do ſee certain excellency in Holineſſe, though diſgraſt and undervalued; if there be any thing in the world that is a ſign of ſincerity it is this, to love Holineſſe when diſgraſt, abuſed, and ſpit upon; to croſſe the ſtream, and thwart the multitude, is a ſign of the truth of Grace, and ſtrength of Grace: This is a ſign of a true ſight, and ſtrong ſight. To ſee beauty in a Godly man in ſufferings, the Lord will certainly have an eye upon thee in times of troubles; Here is comfort in thine infirmities. Doſt thou love Holineſſe when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45865:10"/>compaſſed about with ſufferings and perſecution? God will take notice of thy Grace, though compaſſed about with abundance of infirmities; the Lord will take notice of a little of his, in a great deal of ours: Here's comfort in ſufferings, if you regard his in their ſufferings, the Lord will remember you in your ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the Lord will remember what thou didſt for ſuch and ſuch a Servant of his in trouble or diſtreſſe; God doth not caſt away any in their lowneſſe, that have kept cloſe to him in their highneſſe; and this will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in inward trouble, when thou canſt find nothing from which to fetch comfort. And this will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the laſt day, though we can ſay nothing in that day by way of merit, yet it will be comfort to be able ſincerely to ſay, that thou haſt owned God and his people in the midſt of ſufferings: Do ye think that Judge would not ſave that Malefactor that had ſaved the life of his Wife? If thou haſt owned Chriſt when he was in his rags, do not fear but he will own thee when he comes in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Robes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Inference,</hi> and laſt, The People of God ſhould learn not to be diſcouraged under any miſery or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction that can befall them in this world, at this very time God hath a high eſteem of you; At this time you are his delight, his Garden, his Spouſe. The Saints of God are the wiſemen of the world, they have choſen that which cannot be taken from them: I profeſſe Sirs, the love of one Saint makes amends for all the hatred you undergo from ſinners, the very wicked themſelves have a good opinion of you, when you do not baſely comply, their Conſciences cannot but have an high eſteem of you, when peradventure their tongues might ſpeak againſt you. If all this will not do, remember your own Conſciences are more then a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, for you will then comfort you; No man is a miſerable man for any thing in the world that is done
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45865:10"/>to him, or ſaid of him; No, it is a good Conſcience that will give the beſt acquittance; for thee to have the whole number of Gods people to look upon thee as an unworthy wretch, and as a vile perſon, I look upon it as a greater ignominy and diſgrace, then to have all the diſgraces of wicked men caſt upon thee: That man that hath a Godly man to be afraid of him, had need to be very much afraid of himſelf. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with this one word, There is great reaſon to look narrowly to your hearts and wayes, when they ſtand at a diſtance from you, and are afraid to come near you.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45865:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The After-noon Sermon,</hi> Auguſt 17. 1662</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Text 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of</hi> Exodus, <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Angel of the Lord appeared unto him in a flame of Fire out of the midst of a Buſh, and he looked, and behold the Buſh burned with Fire, and the Buſh was not conſumed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>He read 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5. Verſes.</p>
            <p>THat this may be the more profitable and uſefull, I judge it neceſſary at your leiſure to caſt an eye on the ſore-going Chapter, wherein we ſhall ſee <hi>Moſes</hi> his preſervation: In this Chapter is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed his preparation and fitneſſe for that employment God had appointed him to, by a ſuitable apparition, in which God diſcovers to <hi>Moſes</hi> his care of his People, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> was to be a ſpeedy deliverer.</p>
            <p>In the words read, we have the preparation confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the great work of being called to be <hi>Iſreells</hi> deliverer. In the preparation we may take notice of three principal parts.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45865:11"/>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The Apparition here preſented to <hi>Moſes, A burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet an unconſumed Buſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2d. We have <hi>Moſes</hi> care to obſerve it in theſe words, <hi>I will turn aſide and ſee this great ſight, why the Buſh burns and is not conſumed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3d. We have here Gods monitory precept that he afforded to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he was drawing near to ſee the wonder.</p>
            <p>In the precept or admonition we have principally conſiderable two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. This precept or admonition is propounded, and that is, <hi>That Moſes ſhould not draw near, that he ſhould put off bis Shooes from off his Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2d. The reaſon or argument, whereby God backs this precept or admonition, <hi>Becauſe the place whereon he, ſtood was Holy ground.</hi> Time would faile me ſhould I go over all theſe parts, therefore I ſhall only touch upon the two firſt, namely the apparition that <hi>Moſes</hi> defired to obſerve.</p>
            <p>The apparition was a ſuitable diſcovery of the ſtate of the Church. In the burning, yet unconſuming of the Buſh, obſerve three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Obſerve the lowneſſe and weakneſſe of the Church, repreſented by a Buſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. The cruelty of her Enemies, repreſented by Fire.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. The eminency of its preſervation: Though it was in the Fire, yet it was not conſumed; Not one of theſe but would take me up more time then I have to ſpend upon the whole.</p>
            <p>The Church is compared to a Buſh for two reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. In regard of its deformity and uncomlineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. In regard of its weakneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Church uncomly in regard of thoſe ſufferings. God ſees it good it ſhould be thus to humble his Church, to ſhew his goodneſſe in preſerving of her,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45865:12"/>to make her long for that perfect beauty that ſhe ſhall have: Hereby God makes them the more conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Head: Hereby God makes them look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inward Beauty and Glory: Hereby he puts them upon living a Life of Faith, and not of Senſe: Hereby God ſhews how little he regards the Beauties of this Life: Hereby he ſhews there is a ſtate of reſt and of glory above, that they ſhould look after.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Therefore the people of God are not to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in regard of their deformity, in regard of thoſe ſufferings they undergo in this Life. This Life is the obſcurity of the Churches adoption; we ſee what ſhe is, but not what ſhe ſhall be.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. We ſhould take heed of expecting that Glory that God hath not promiſed, it is too much to have two Heavens.</p>
            <p n="3">3d. Hereby we may ſee the reaſon why wicked men ſtumble ſo much at the Church of God, it is becauſe there is nothing of outſide Beauty and Glory to take them, or to allure them.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The Church of God is compared to a Buſh, in regard of its weakneſs, not to a ſtrong Oak, but to a Buſh, in other places to a Vine, both of them weak; to a Dove, a Lamb, a Sheep, weak creatures, ſometimes ſaid to be deſtitute; As our Lord Ieſus the Head of the Church, ſuffered through weakneſſe, ſo God hereby makes them reſt upon him, and when they are weak in themſelves, then are they ſtrong. The weakneſſe of our State, ſhews the ſtrength of the Grace of God afforded to them in upholding of them, the weakneſſe of the Church wonderfully confounds her Enemies, to be delivered not only againſt the ſtrength of men, but by the oppoſitions of men. Hereby the People of God are made more thankfull, both for their Preſervation, and likewiſe for their deliverance from their ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Adverſaries; I am too long on this which I thought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45865:12"/>only to have toucht upon. Here's a larg Field, which whether moſt ſuitable to the Text or the Times, I ſhall leave others to judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The Enemies of the Church are compared to fire, the fire of affliction doth not only diſcover to us their rage and cruelty, but likewiſe diſcovers the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that comes to the Church by afflictions, afflictions are not conſuming fire, but trying fire, God teacheth his Servants excellent Leſſons by the light of this fire.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. The Emminency of their Preſervation; they are not conſumed, though the fire be never ſo ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it looſes in one place, ſo it gains in another, God will have his number, the Enemyes of the Church may as well attempt to beat the Sun with Snow-balls, or blow it out of the Heavens with Bellows, as to drive the Church of God out of the world, their Graves are not conſumed, this fire doth not burn them up, though it burn upon them, God will not ſuffer this fire to exceed their ſtrength, it ſhall burn up nothing but their droſſe, that that would deſtroy them, if not deſtroyed out of them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſſe by the 2d. generall part, <hi>viz. Moſes</hi> his care to obſerve it. <hi>Moſes</hi> was an excellent Naturaliſt, yet he could ſee no reaſon in nature, that a flaming fire ſhould be in a Buſh, and the Buſh not burnt; I do not think that <hi>Moſes</hi> turned aſide in curioſity, ſo much as to ſee what God did intend by this great miracle: When Gods works are great, our obſervations ſhould not be ſmall, when the hand of God is eminently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered we ſhould not ſhut our eyes. I am farr from being a Fanatick, or led by unſcripturall grounds, yet I cannot but obſerve the Hand of God, in theſe dayes wherein we now live, we have ſeen and heard of ſtrange ſights, wonderfull wonders, and I queſtion whether there hath not been ſomething as ſtrange as this, the hand of God is not to be neglected, though it cannot be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45865:13"/>perfectly underſtood; It is a ſign of a wicked man, to have the works of God out of his fight. Sirs, you may truſt this God that hath wrought ſuch wonders as in our, dayes he hath done, he hath all the creatures at his command, we ſhould dread and ſtand in awe of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this God.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. We have here conſider able the Monitory admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of God; In that he doth forbid <hi>Moſes</hi> to draw nigh, and then he doth bid him to pull off his Shoes, the reaſon of the former will be underſtood by the opening of the latter, I ſhall briefly take notice of two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An injunction, <hi>Put of thy Shooes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The argument, <hi>becauſe the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not give you the ſeverall gloſſes of ſome Criticks upon the words, the plain meaning is this, Gods ſcope and drift is to require of <hi>Moſes</hi> reverence, when he was to draw nigh to him; His deſign herein was to prepare him for obedience, and therefore God required that of him, which ſome Servants were wont to do, when they came before their Lords, or Maſters, to teſtifie their reverence to thoſe before whom they came, it was an ancient cuſtome, I might ſpend the hour in giving you inſtances or examples to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; This <hi>Galeatius</hi> obſerves; the bareing the feet or putting off the Shooes, is in Scripture held forth as a token of reverence: Hence we read of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, as having his Shooes on, and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as unworthy to unty his Shoo-lachets. Iſaiah 20.2. <hi>And the ſame time ſpake the Lord by</hi> Iſaiah <hi>the ſon of</hi> Amoz, <hi>ſaying, Go, and looſe the ſackloth from off thy loins, and put off thy Shoe from thy foot: and he did ſo, walking naked and bare-foot.</hi> Ezekiel 24.17. <hi>Forbear to cry, make no mourning for the dead, bind the tire of thine head upon thee, and put on thy Shooes upon thy feet, and cover not thy lips, and eat not the bread of men.</hi> Mourners are there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45865:13"/>ſaid to go unſhod, to note ſubmiſſion or ſubjection: On the other ſide, when God would ſhow the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of his people, he is ſaid to put on Shooes on their feet: So the reception of the Prodigall into his Fathers houſe, is according to the judgement of ſome learned men, intended by that expreſſion, the putting on Shooes on his feet, Luke 15.22. <hi>But the Father ſaid to his Servants, bring forth the beſt Robe, and put it on him; and put a ring on his hand, and Shoes on his feet.</hi> As much as if God had ſaid ſhew thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, due ſubmiſſiveneſſe and ſubjection of Spirit, together with thy ſervile readineſſe, to do whatever I ſhall command and enjoyn: <hi>Calvin</hi> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent note upon this place. If ſo excellent a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, had need to be quickened by ſuch a Ceremony as this was, doubtleſſe we who are more backward to obedience, we ſhould both ſignifie the reverence of our ſouls by outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and of our bodies by bodily geſture, by knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, lifting up the hand, and the like, the preſence of God is great; We that are by the law of Creation much below him, and by the illegall Law of Sin much againſt him, ſhould certainly ſhow our Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when he calls to us or wee addreſſe to him The reaſon, becauſe the place whereon <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtood was holy ground: It was holy in regard of this miraculous Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not as if the place were of its own Nature holy, but God doth hereby import, that that place by the ſpeciall Teſtimony of his preſence, in relation to the miracle, becauſe he was miraculouſly there preſent, that made the place holy: Thus it was then, I do not underſtand how I can ſo profitably diſcourſe of this unto you, unleſſe I take notice of the holineſſe of places now in the times of the Goſple, and conſider, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt </seg>
               </label> how one place may be ſaid to be more holy then another.</p>
            <p>I was not willingly put upon this imployment, if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45865:14"/>it had not been extorted from mee by ſomething that I have ſeen formerly and lately written, and by ſome, and thoſe not of the Leaneſt or Ignorant, but moſt Learned and accounted moſt Knowing. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tells us theſe words <q>The Temples conſecration is deſervedly holy and venerable, and indued with a divine efficacie and vertue: ſo Great is the Holineſſe of Churches, that thoſe things may be forbidden perpetually to be done in them, which may be lawfully done elſewhere.</q> Here I ſhall Endeavour to explain the Queſtion, then Try, and faithfully reſolve it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the opening of it: 1. I ſhall ſhew you what it is for a place to be holy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What that is that is the foundation or cauſe of the Holineſs of places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> For the firſt, What it is for a place to be holy, wherein the Nature of a place's holineſſe doth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, Firſt Generally, Secondly more Particularly. Firſt Generally, The Holineſſe of a place conſiſts in the Separation thereof, the ſetting of it apart, exalting of it above and before other places, thus the Notion of Holineſſe is taken in Scripture in 30 <hi>Exodus ver.</hi> 31. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſpeak unto the children of Iſrael, ſaying, This ſhall be an holy anointing oyl to me thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your generations.</hi> You ſhall there read concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Ointment that He preſcribes to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for his ſervice, it was ſet apart only for that purpoſe: The Holineſſe there of conſiſted in the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it from other uſes and other oyles, in the 37, &amp; 38 verſes of the ſame Chapter, <hi>And as for the perſume which thou ſhalt make, you ſhall not make to your ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the compoſition thereof, it ſhall be unto thee, holy for the Lord; Whoſoever ſhall make like unto to ſmell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſhall even be cut off from his people.</hi> The like we have in the zoth of <hi>Leviticus</hi> 24 and 25 verſes. <hi>But I have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45865:14"/>ſaid unto you, Ye ſhall inherit their land, and I will give it unto you to poſſeſſe it, a land that floweth with milk and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: I am the Lord your God which have ſeparated you from other people. Ye ſhall therefore put difference between clean beaſts and unclean, and between unclean fowles and clean: and ye ſhall not make your ſouls abominable by beaſts or by fowl, or by any maner of living thing, that creepeth on the ground, which I have ſeparated from you as unclean.</hi> 26 Deuteronomy 18, and 19, <hi>verſes. And the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath promiſed thee, and that thou ſhouldest keep all his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; And to make thee high above all Nations which he hath made, in praiſe, and in name, and in honour, and that thou mayeſt be an holy people unto the Lord thy God, as he hath ſpoken.</hi> God is ſaid there to avouch his people to bee his, and his. becauſe he is ſaid to have Separated them: For this take two Scriptures more, 19 <hi>Deut.</hi> 2. &amp; 7. verſes. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſeparate three cities for thee in the midst of thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee to poſſeſſe it; Wherefore I command thee ſaying, Thou ſhalt ſeparate three Cities for thee.</hi> And in the 20th of <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the 2d. verſe, and ſo on. That which in one place is called <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> in the other place is called <hi>Sanctification.</hi> And hence it is, that a thing is ſaid to be unholy, when it is Common, and not ſet apart to holy Uſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.14. <hi>But Peter ſaid, Not ſo, Lord; for I have never eaten any thing that is common or unclean.</hi> Hebr. 10.29. <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the bloud of the Covenant wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite unto the Spirit of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. This ſetting apart of places for holy uſes, muſt have two properties:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be alienated from other uſes to holy uſes, the imploying of them to civil uſes, muſt be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as ſinfull and unlawfull, when Times or Things or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45865:15"/>Perſons are reputed holy when they are to be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Common Imployment. The Sabbath day, an Holy day, Common imployment muſt not be done on that day. The veſſels of the Tabernacle they were holy, not to be imployed in ordinary uſes. Some ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted this to be the ſinne of <hi>Belſhazzer,</hi> becauſe he uſed the veſſels of the Temple. Thus the oyl and the oyntment fore-mentioned.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. More particularly concerning this Holineſſe. This muſt be ſuch a ſeparation, as a ſervice done to God in thoſe places muſt be accounted and look'd upon as a Bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſervice, and more acceptable, thon if it had been don elſwhere: As places are ſaid to be holy, becauſe they only are to be for Holy ſervices, &amp; Holy ſervices are only to be done in thoſe Holy places. My Brethren, I defire you to take Notice, Places were ſaid to be Holy which did ſanctifie the Worſhip that was done in them, and ſanctified the Worſhipper. The very places were part of Worſhip. Theſe places were not only thoſe in which God was worſhipped, but by which God was worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Thus the Sabboth was ſanctified, and ſo the Altar, when that was Holy and Sanctified, it made the Gift to be ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Ye fools and blinde; for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ether is greater, the gift, or the Altar that ſanctifieth the Gift.</hi> The Altar you ſee ſanctified the gift, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Services done in ſuch Garments more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, becauſe done in ſuch Garments.</p>
            <p>More generally in reſpect of ſeparation, the cauſe and foundation of a place or any other things holineſſe, is its belonging to God, Gods propriety and peculiar relation to it, therefore to be holy, and to be Gods, are in Scripture equivolent, its being Gods, and God having relation and propriety to it, makes it become holy. Exodus. 13.2. <hi>Sanctifie unto me all the firſt-born, whatſoever opens the worth among the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>both of man and of beast, it is mine.</hi> God commands that they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45865:15"/>ſhould ſanctifie to him all the firſt born, they ſhall be holy to me whatſoever opens the womb, it is mine; The cauſe and reaſon of its being holy, it becauſe it is Gods. Luke 2.23. <hi>(As it is written in the Law of the Lord, every male that openeth the womb, ſhall be called holy to the Lord.)</hi> This command is there again repeated, but in other words, as it is written, every male that openeth the womb, ſhall be holy unto the Lord; That which in one place is ſaid to be ſeparated, is here ſaid to be holy, and therefore holy becauſe ſeparated by God: Yet more particularly, the declared propriety that God hath in any place, or its belonging to God, is declared two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. From his preſence.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. From his precepts.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt From his preſence, extraordinary or ordinary.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Extraordinary, the extraordinary preſence of God is ſeen by his miraculous diſcovering of himſelf, by ſome ſign, as here in the Buſh. Joſhua 5.15. <hi>And the Captain of the Lords boſt ſaid unto</hi> Joſhua, <hi>looſe thy Shee from off thy foot, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy, and</hi> Joſhua <hi>did ſo.</hi> Hence it is that in 2 Pet. 1.18. <hi>And this voyce which came from Heaven, we heard, when we were with him in the holy Mount.</hi> The Mountain of Chriſts transfiguration is called the holy Mountain; There was an extraordinary manifeſtation of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo long as that continued, that was called an holy Mountain, this ceaſing, the holyneſſe of the place ceaſed likewiſe; <hi>Peter</hi> did not call it holy, becauſe it was ſo when he writ, but becauſe it had been ſo, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would have been unlawfull, to have imployed it to any other uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2d. His ordinary preſence makes a place holy, the preſence of the ſtanding Reſidency by ſome externall Symboll. 2d. His ſpeciall preſence in the religious Services of his people, concerning the firſt of theſe;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45865:16"/>this was confirmed in the Time of the Ceremonial Law, as inſtance <hi>the Altar, the Temple, the Ark, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-Seat,</hi> They were all Symbolis and ſignes of Gods preſence amongſt his people, That God was truly preſent in a more then ordinary way to do them good, He recorded his name there, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68.1. where its ſaid, <hi>Let God ariſe, and his Enemies be ſcattered.</hi> Hence it was they mourned ſo much for the taking of the Ark, becauſe the viſible ſign of Gods preſence was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away: ſo long as theſe continued, He was look'd upon as there, and thither the people went to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Gods ordinary preſence is conſiderable in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſervices of his people. This I call the Spiritual preſence of God in his Ordinances, 18 <hi>Matth. verſe</hi> 20. <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them:</hi> Not in the Midſt of the place, but of the people, Praying, Preaching, Sacraments, in the due diſpenſation thereof he is preſent to accept them, His Spiritual preſence to bleſſe them, His preſence there to Aſſiſt in the due performance of them: Neither can his preſence be ordinarily expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but in his own wayes.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. As the preſence of God is the cauſe of a place its holineſſe, ſo Gods propriety and relation to a place is declared by his precept: He may chooſe whom he will, and what place he will. He unto whom all things belong, may more peculiarly have ſomething belong to him than others. Thus the Temple and the Tabernacle of old, they were conſecrated and ſet apart for God, by vertue of his divine command. 1ſt. He muſt have them Juſt according to the pattern. 2. He commanded them to be done in ſuch a place, and in no other. Here in this place is Typified Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God commanded the people to come to this place to worſhip Three times a Year, as in <hi>Exodus</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45865:16"/>23 <hi>verſe</hi> 17. <hi>Three times a year all thy males ſhall appear before the Lord God.</hi> 3dly. He commanded that people ſhould reverence theſe places, and forbid all Civill Imployment to be done there. 4thly. He made a promiſe to that place that he would accept the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties done there, becauſe done there. That was the reaſon why the people prayed in the Temple, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in their own Houſes, and when they could not be preſent there, if they but looked toward the Temple, God accepted, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 8. verſ. 44, 45. <hi>If thy people go out to battel againſt their enemy, whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſhalt ſend them, and ſhall pray unto the Lord toward the City which thou haſt choſen, and toward the Houſe that I have built for thy name; Then hear thou in heaven their prayer and their ſupplication, and maintain their cauſe, &amp;c.</hi> This ſhews the reaſon and foundation of any place its Holineſſe, The Preſence of God, and the Precept of God.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the reſolution of this Queſtion: <hi>viz.</hi> How one place can be ſaid to be more Holy then another in the Times of the Goſpell: and I ſhall reſolve it, Firſt, by granting what muſt not be denyed. 2dly. By denying what muſt not be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By Granting that which muſt not be denyed, and herein, I ſhall <hi>Grant</hi> theſe 4. things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That in the Time of the Goſpel it is not only Lawfull, but very commendable to deſign and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate places to Holy Services: When I ſay it is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and commendable to deſign and dedicate places, I do not ſay to Conſecrate and Sanctifie them. There's a vaſt difference between the deſigning or appointing, or dedicating, and the Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crating that place. Firſt, Concerning the deſigning or appointing of a place for any holy Imployment, differs much from Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating it. A day may be appointed for the doing of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45865:17"/>any work in, but it is not conſecrated. We may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to meet in ſuch a place, and if prevented may meet in another. Secondly, The place we dedicate muſt be our own, in our own right to give, ſo to give it, as not to recall it. It is Lawfull for a Rich man to dedicate ſuch a place to ſuch an uſe, or ſuch a ſumme of money to Build a School or an Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, ſo that it ſhall not be in his power to recall it. By the way, this Dedication in Times of the Goſpel differs from the Dedication of any thing or place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in Times of the Law, for they were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly dedicated to God as part of Worſhip, whereas now it is not ſo. Thoſe things were holy, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their Dedication, but becauſe of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Acceptation: Conſecration is a great deal more; That makes it ſo Holy, that there muſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done in it, but what it is appointed to. The Services performed in thoſe places muſt be more acceptable to God, and efficacious to the performers that do perform them.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. I grant ſome places are to have their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Services performed in them, rather then others: I mean places of greater conveniency, places appointed for publick meeting, rather then private, where we have the example of good to joyn together, and go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with us, thus thoſe of old overcame the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. I deſire you to bear me witneſſe this day, that I plead for publick Ordinances, where Ordinances are pure, without humane mixture; I do here profeſſe, and do avowedly declare its my judgement, if they may be injoyed purely, I am for publick Ordinances.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. During the time of performing Religious Services, we are not to uſe ſecular or civil imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as eating, drinking, &amp;c. all which is lawfull at other times, but unlawfull then, being contrary to an expreſſe command: <hi>Let every thing be done decently, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45865:17"/>in order.</hi> We are to abſtain from theſe things, when the Miniſter is preaching, you are not then to clap your ſelf upon your knees, as is the cuſtome of too many, that plead for Vniformity, in that and in many other practiſes they croſſe the thing they moſt plead for.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. I grant that after the performance of holy duties in theſe places wherein we meet, its our duty to abſtein from, not only filthy and undecent actions, but from thoſe civil lawfull actions, that may reflect any diſhonour on the work that hath been done there, all that is to be done that may render the place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet, for Religious Services afterwards. This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence not due, becauſe the place is more holy, but for decency and order things ſubſervient to Religion call for reverence, and are not to be uſed, ſo that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Services are to be made deſpicable; The Bread of the Sacrament is not to be caſt to unreaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe it reflects a diſhonour upon the Service, neither ſhould dirty puddle be put into the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Cup, becauſe it reflects diſhonour to the uſe its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to, this is civil reference due to any place, where there is a Senate met in a Parliament houſe, in a Kings bed-chamber, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I come now to deny what is not to be granted, and likewiſe I deny four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That its not now in the times of the Goſpell, in any mans power, to ſet a part a place for Religious duties, ſo but it may be lawfull upon a due occaſion, to uſe it for a civil imployment, or its not unlawfull to alienate ſuch places to other uſes, then it was deſigned; The Bread and Wine in the Sacrament, after publick uſing them, is not unlawfull to be eaten in a civil way, ſo that we do not diſhonour God thereby, neither is there any more holineſſe in them then before. The Synagogues were as holy as our Churches are, they were appointed for prayer, and preaching, and reading,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45865:18"/>and were dedicated to holy Uſes, yet there were Civil imployments in thoſe places. Here among us we Conſecrate places; I doe affirm only God can make a thing or place ſo holy, that it ſhall be a ſin to imploy it to any other uſe. And if the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church ſhall ſubſtitute other things or other places for divine imployment, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thoſe formerly uſed, then thoſe former places and things returns to their accuſtomed uſe again, for the Pulpit, or Communion table, or the Surpliſs, or any other Veſtment, when done uſing, are not to be burnt, or buried under the Altar, but may be uſed to Common and Ordinary Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments; the Communion Cup is no more holyer then the Wine, they may be uſed as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things without fear of Sin; to Conſecrate moveable things, or unmoveable things ſo, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may not uſe them, is abominable Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. God hath not appointed theſe things to be uſed ſo, as none may ever uſe them otherwayes. Theſe things are not holy in themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. No place in the times of the Goſpell hath ſuch holineſſe either from Inſtitution or uſe, as to ſanctifie or make acceptable or effectuall the ſervice therein performed, this is not in the times of the Goſpel. God is preſent at the places of Religious performances, not in reſpect of the place, but to the performers. Therefore God doth not ſay I will be preſent in that place, for the places ſake, but for the duties ſake. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45865:18"/>in the time of the Ceremonial Law were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded for the places ſake; but we muſt abhor this piece of <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> and utterly deny Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this day of the Goſpel, when the Altar ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified the Gift, this is done by Gods inſtitution; But to ſay places or things can now do ſo, it makes the appointments of men, equall with the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God. The Temple ſanctified the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or performances, not they the Temple; its quite contrary now: Our Churches and Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are not holy, without relation to the duties performed; Our duties are holy, without relation to the Church, but the Church not holy without relation to the duties therein performed: None but God can conſecrate a place to bee an effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall means of Worſhip. The Jewes worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Temple, Now God is worſhipped elſewhere, the places have no influence at all into our duties, at the moſt but helpfull to the bodies Conveniency.</p>
            <p>The third thing I deny is this; There is now no place ſo holy, as to exclude another place from being as holy; we have not now the precept of God to preferr one place above another; Wee have not now the miraculous preſence of God, God hath not given us thoſe Symbolls of his ſtanding reſidency amongſt us, as in former dayes he did his People, as the <hi>Arke',</hi> the <hi>Mercy Seat, &amp;c.</hi> As for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45865:19"/>his Ordinances and the performance of them; if we make a Place holy, in regard of Gods ſpeciall and ſpirituall preſence, I ſay the Cloſet, or Dining Room, or Chamber, the Field, or the River ſide is holy, humane conſecration make no place truly holy: I ſay it again, its the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance maketh one place more holy then another, then any Utenſils in the Church are more holy then the Church, the Font and the Communion Table, then the body of the Church, and ſo you make a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween holyneſſe, in holy places, in holy things, and ſo bring in plain <hi>Judaiſme;</hi> A new Table where the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was never adminiſtred, cannot be ſo holy as the old, by this the very Mouthes of the Communicants would be ſo holy, that they muſt not eat nor drink any more, but they would defile it: I conclude this with this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, that Religious difference of places is removed, the Goſpel takes it quite away, the Goſpel is ſo far from giving or making ſuch a difference. 1. Tim. 2.8. <hi>I will therefore that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wrath and doubting.</hi> John 4.21, 22, 23. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto her, Woman, believe me the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, not yet at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ye worſhip ye know not what: we know what we worſhip: for Salvation is of the Jews. But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in truth: for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at</hi> Corinth, <hi>to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours.</hi> Therefore <hi>where two or three are met together, there am I in the middeſt of them,</hi> Mat. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.</p>
            <p>This is the ſum of all, That Gods inſtitution is to be regarded, humane inſtitution to be rejected.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:45865:19"/>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, No place is ſo ſanctified by the miraculous ſpecial preſence of God, but that preſence ceaſes, when the tokens of Gods reſidence ceaſe; the Ark, the Mercy-ſeat, the places became as before.</p>
            <p>For us to go a pilgrimage to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is an abominable thing; how many bloody battels have ſince been ſought there? theſe places where the preſence of God was, when abuſed to the diſhonour of God, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe and worſe: whatever we uſe in holy uſes, looſes their holineſſe when abuſed. It's boldneſſe for us to tye the preſence of God to any place, for God hath not tyed himſelf to any place. I cannot but wonder, how it's poſſible for men to hold, that the Lords day, which God hath been pleaſed to ſet apart for himſelf, that its holineſſe can ceaſe; for that they ſay, the Lords day is not holier longer than the ſervice is in doing; yet that the Church, that God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appointed, ſhould retain its holineſſe, that you muſt not tread there, but with your hat off, nor come there without bowing the knee.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to wind up all with profitable inferences that floweth from hence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. The firſt inference: See the great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſanctity and holineſſe of places under the Old, and under the New Teſtament. Thoſe under the Old, had the miraculous preſence of God: ſo long the places were holy. They had their Temple, their Altar, their Mercy-ſeat, the Ark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe places were holy; you cannot ſay the like now: we have the preſence of God, but we have not the precept of God, as they had: places now differ from places then.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. I note the great goodneſſe of God, to give to us ſuch a ſweet diſpenſation, that now hee doth not tye us to places, as heretofore he did the <hi>Jenes:</hi> no land now is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, nor place now holier then another: every coaſt is a <hi>Iudea,</hi> every Congregation is now a <hi>Zion,</hi> a Temple: you may pray as well now in your cloſets, as then in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:45865:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. There are ſeveral perſons to be reproved; thoſe that take pilgrimages to particular places, becauſe of that holineſſe they ſuppoſe in them. I might tell you of their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reliques: I will not trouble you with them: ſuppoſe them true, what is this to Inſtitution and command of God? where have you a command for ſuch a thing? I might take notice of thoſe that put holineſſe in places of Burial; in the Church; think it holier than the Church-yard; and one part of the Church holier than another; private prayer, rather than joyn in publick: for any to bow towards the place of the Communion Table, rather than to any other place of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. I ſhall deſire you to take notice of four things, you that are Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let this encourage you to ſerve God in your Families, and places that God hath ſet you in, with humility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as becomes that God with whom you have to do. Though I am againſt Superſtition, and Popiſh Innovations, yet I am for poſitive reverence wherever. <hi>Abraham</hi> came, he built God an Altar. Let no morning or evening paſſe, without Prayer in your Families; Pray, pray often: let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of your houſes be a Church: this will bring a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on the place where you live. Be much in Prayer, for the Lords ſake.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Labour to promote perſonal Holineſſe, as well as Family duty. Since you have heard ſomething of holineſſe of places, let us labour to become holy. Do you think thoſe wretches are not the more to be lamented, that ſwear, and drink, and lye, and whore, and think that the very duſt of the Temple touching their garments, will make them Holy? oh, put away uncleanneſſe, pride, drunkenneſſe, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, elſe though you bow and cringe, God will not hear your Prayers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Love the holineſſe of the living Temples of God; wherever thou ſeeſt any thing of holineſſe, be in love with that ſoul: if there be a heaven upon earth, it is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the company of Saints: this will blow up the coals of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45865:20"/>ſpiritual love to God and goodneſſe. A famous man had this expreſſion, When I was in the company of Saints, I thought I was as if I had been among living coales; but when I was ſeparated from them, and came among Swearers and Drunkards, I found a ſpiritual frozenneſſe all over mee. Though the people of God are beſt company in Heaven, yet they are good company on earth. Whatever thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, impart it: Grace may be imparted, it cannot be impaired.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Labour to preſerve the holineſſe of Gods true Inſtitutions; thoſe things that are of divine conſecration. For humane conſecration, alas what is it? But for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, the Lords day, labour to keep it holy. We talk much of Holy dayes, this is ſo indeed. The Lords Supper, that's of Divine Inſtitution, labour for a holy participation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. If any thing in the world would drive mee to a Paſſion, this would, to hear men plead for the holineſſe of places, and live unholy Lives; to ſtand up for humane, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard Divine inſtitutions. Oh that our King and Parliament might do ſomething more than is done for keeping the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both holy! oh that we could mourn for that we cannot mend! The Sacraments are Holy: it is the duty of Miniſters to labour to keep them holy. The Lords Word that's Holy. Miniſtry, and the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, labour to keep in High eſteem. We ought to hear with the ſame reverence, as if Jeſus Chriſt himſelf was here to preach. Live like walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Temples. Many of theſe truths might be further inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but <hi>I</hi> have not time nor ſtrength. I could diſcharge my duty, without ſpeaking ſomthing to theſe. What you have received with the right hand, do not eaſt off with the left: I have better hopes of you, my dearly beloved: I hope God will bring home theſe, and all other thoſe truths to your ſoules, which in much weakneſſe I have delivered to you: and be more to you, than his poor Miniſter, though he ſhould have remained with you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
